A Finding Aid to the Glen Lukens Papers, 1920-1983, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Glen Lukens papers
1920-1983
Archives of American Art
Lukens, Glen
AAA.lukeglen
Archival Resource Key
1.6 Linear feet
The papers of ceramicist Glen Lukens measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1983. The bulk of the papers consist of letters from Lukens to family members, and other correspondence with family, friends, and colleagues. Notably, letters describe Lukens' time working in Haiti to establish a ceramic industry, his views on United States involvement in World War II, and the Watts Riots in Los Angeles in 1965. Also found are biographical materials, scattered writings and notes on ceramics and other subjects, printed materials, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Glen Lukens (1887-1967) was a ceramicist, educator, and writer active in Southern California. He taught at the University of Southern California where he founded the school's ceramics department and later established the ceramics industry in Haiti.
Glen Lukens was born in Missouri and attended the Oregon State Agricultural School where he was introduced to ceramics. He proved to be an innovator and created a blue glaze made out of metals he found in the Mojave desert. Lukens was active with a group of studio ceramicists, including Beatrice Wood, who elevated the artform through writing, innovation, and teaching. Lukens created simple pottery with bold color and glazing techniques. He spent much of his career teaching ceramics at the University of Southern California but also worked with glass and created jewelry.
In the 1940s, Lukens traveled to Haiti to teach ceramics and establish an industry for the creation of pottery on the island. Lukens was focused on teaching Haitians to use sanitary clay vessels for food rather than gourds. He formed friendships with many of his students and encouraged their further study of ceramics in the United States.
Glen Lukens died in Los Angeles in 1967.
Scope and Contents
The papers of ceramicist Glen Lukens measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1983. The bulk of the papers consist of letters from Lukens to family members, and other correspondence with family, friends, and colleagues. Notably, letters describe Lukens' time working in Haiti to establish a ceramic industry, his views on United States involvement in World War II, and the Watts Riots in Los Angeles in 1965. Also found are biographical materials, scattered writings and notes on ceramics and other subjects, printed materials, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on 35mm microfilm reels 5662-5663 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the order of the material on microfilm.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Glen Lukens papers were donated by his niece, Vera O'Dell in 1983.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds the Glen Lukens letters to Roy Walker, circa 1930-1945. The collection contains about 150 letters from Lukens to Roy Walker.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1920-1977 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1933-1983 (1.0 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV5)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1937-circa 1960 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1940s-1960s (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1936-1966 (0.6 linear feet; Box 3-4)
- Biographical Material, 1920-1977; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Found are biographical sketches of Glen Lukens, awards and certificates, lists of family and friends, receipts, and Lukens' will and estate papers.
  - Awards, Certificates, and Honorary Diplomas, 1920-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Sketches, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of Family and Friends, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Receipts and Sales, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Will and Estate Papers, 1950s-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Correspondence, 1933-1983; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1-2, OV5
  Glen Lukens correspondence contains letters from friends and colleagues and scattered letters from family members. Found are many letters Lukens wrote to his aunt by marriage Carlotta Lukens, sister Edith Lukens Stone, and niece Vera Stone O'Dell. His letters often discuss his works and experimental techniques, career, feelings on race relations within the United States and Haiti, and his disappointment with the United States' involvement in World War II.
  Notable correspondents include Albert M. Johnson, Mryton Purkiss, Congressman Will Rogers, and Beatrice Wood. Letters from Lukens' students, written while serving in World War II and from Haitian students Marcus Douton and Hugo Racine comment on Lukens' involvement and connection to his students. Included are two illustrated letters, one by H.C. Westermann and the other by Glen Lukens sent to his niece, Vera O'Dell.
  - Alfred University, 1949-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - B, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - B, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Casper, Avanelle and Don, 1943-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - County of Los Angeles, California, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - C, 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Doty, Walter, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Douyon, Marcus, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Eastman, Alfred, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fullerton District Junior College, 1933, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Gould, Nancy, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Griffin, Karl, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Haden, Mary Jane, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hayward, Virginia, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - J, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lord & Taylor, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lukens, Mrs. Carlotta, 1944-1959, circa 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27-34)
  - Maud, Anna, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Myers, Alice C., 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - M, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - N, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Oakland Art Museum, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - O'Dell, Vera and Boyd, 1950s-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Pinto, Alfred, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Poor People's Corporation, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Purkiss, Myrton, 1939-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - R, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Scripps College, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Society of Designer Craftsmen, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Stone, Mrs. Ellis (Edith), 1931-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - United Nations, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - University of Southern California, Los Angeles, 1944-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Wallach, Violet, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Westermann, H..C., 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Wood, Beatrice, 1935-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - First Names Only, 1938, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56-57)
  - First Names Only or Illegible, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Letters Regarding Watts Riots, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters Regarding Glen Lukens, Condolences, 1967-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Empty Envelopes, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Painted Letter, H.C. Westermann, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1937-circa 1960; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series contains speeches given at an award luncheon in honor of Glen Lukens for Lord and Taylor department store and scattered notes by Glen Lukens on ceramics and clay. Works by others include poetry and a play and are likely by former students of Lukens. Signed works are by Ruby Berkley Goodwin, C.M.Henson, Vachel Lindsay, and Jacqueline Preston Peabody.
  - Speeches, from Lord & Taylor Design Award Luncheon, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes, on Clay and Ceramics, circa 1937-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - by Others, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Printed Material, 1940s-1960s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed materials consist of clippings, including articles by Lukens, exhibition catalogs, blank postcards, and press releases.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, by Glen Lukens, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, on Ceramics, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, General, 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Postcards, Blank, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Press Releases, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Photographs, circa 1936-1966; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Black and white photographs depict Lukens at work and in his studio; his home; Carlotta Lukens; Haiti; works of art by Lukens including a portfolio submitted to the Society of Designer Craftsmen of New York City; and works by others.
  - of Glen Lukens, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - of Carlotta Lukens, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - of Studio, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - of Home, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - of Haiti, Includes Writings, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bust of Lukens, by Henry Lyons, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Portfolio, Society of Designer Craftsmen, circa 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Used in Articles, circa 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Works of Art, circa 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-18)
  - Works of Art, by Marcus Douyon, circa 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Works of Art, by Myrton Purkiss, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Works of Art, European (Tourist Photos), circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Negatives and Transparencies, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-5)